Mr. And Mrs. Alison , Car 96 ,
Compartment F , Orient Express , Budapest .
- Darling .
- Peter .
- Aren 't you hungry ?
- No , darling .
Are you ?
- No , of course not .
- Are you sure ?
- I 'm starved .
- So am I.
- I didn 't eat a bite at luncheon .
- Well , neither did I.
Whoever eats anything at a wedding luncheon ?
They make the food out of papier mache .
My salad had been used four or five times this week .
Shall we dine in , Mrs. Alison ?
- You mean here in the compartment ?
- Yes .
- Elegant .
- Excuse me , sir , lady .
A terrible mistake has occurred .
We have sold space in your compartment to a gentlemen .
It is terrible .
- Well ?
- You are going only to Visegrád
which arrives at two o 'clock .
Might you perhaps make room for this gentleman ?
- Do please forgive this intrusion .
It is not necessary to make it so important .
You need not disturb these people .
I can make myself quite comfortable in the passageway .
- Oh , we 're only going as far as Visegrád .
You 're entirely welcome to share this compartment
if you wish .
- You 're very kind .
Thank you .
Sorry .
- That 's all right .
- Thank you .
Wait .
- Sorry I frightened you , darling .
- It is after all , better to be frightened
than to be crushed .
- Well , I 'm Peter Alison .
This is Mrs. Alison .
- It is very great pleasure .
I 'm Dr. Vitus Werdegast .
So , you are going to Visegrád ?
Yes , and to Grumbach by bus .
- Ah , Grumbach is very beautiful .
I too , am going very near there .
For the sport ?
- Perhaps .
I go to visit an old friend .
May I ?
Certainly .
- I beg your indulgence , my friend .
18 years ago , I left a girl
so like your lovely wife to go to war .
Kaiser and country , you know .
She was my wife .
Have you ever heard of Kurgaal ?
It is a prison below .
Many men have gone there .
Few have returned .
I have returned .
After 15 years ,
Go ahead , my servant is coming .
- It is too bad about the rain .
It 's very unusual .
This road was built by the Austrian army .
All of this country was one of the greatest
battlefields of the war .
Tens of thousands of men died here .
The ravine down there was piled 12 deep
with dead and wounded men .
The little river below was swollen ,
a red , raging torrent of blood .
That high hill yonder where Engineer Poelzig now lives
was the site of Fort Marmaris .
He built his home on its very foundation .
Marmaris , the greatest graveyard in the world .
- Driver is dead .
Engineer Poelzig ?
Herr Poelzig has retired .
- Engineer Poelzig will be expecting me .
I 'm Dr. Werdegast .
We 've had a bad accident .
Awaken Herr Poelzig at once and take us somewhere
where I can dress the lady 's injury .
A man was killed .
Telephone the gendarme in Visegrád and inform them .
- Dr. Werdegast has arrived .
- There is no need to worry .
I 'm sure after a good night 's sleep ,
she will be quite all right .
It has been a long time , Hjalmar .
The years have been kind to you .
An accident on the road below .
We are all very fortunate to be alive .
Mr. and Mrs. Alison are going to Grumbach .
Mrs. Alison is slightly injured .
I took the liberty of bringing them here .
- Of course .
- She will sleep now .
You sold Marmaris to the Russians .
Scattered away in the night and left us to die .
Is it to be wondered at that you should choose
this place to build your house ?
A masterpiece of construction
built upon the ruins of the masterpiece of destruction ,
the masterpiece of murder .
The murdererer of 10,000 men
returns to the place of his crime .
Those who died were fortunate .
I was taken prisoner to Kurgaal .
Kurgaal , where the soul is killed ,
slowly .
15 years I rotted in the darkness .
Wait .
Not to kill you .
To kill your soul , slow .
Where 's my wife , Karen , and my daughter ?
- Karen ?
Well , what do you mean ?
- I mean you told Karen I had been killed .
I found out that much in Budapest .
I mean , you always wanted her .
In the days but before the war ,
always , from the first time you saw her .
I mean that after you saved your own hide
and left us all to die in Marmaris ,
you went to Karen , induced her to go to America with you .
I trace the two of you there
and to Spain and to South America and finally here .
Where is she ?
- Vitus , you are mad .
- Where is she ?
- Sorry if I 'm intruding .
- Not at all .
Do come in .
We were just going to have something to drink .
Now , perhaps you 'll join us .
And what would you like ?
- Oh , whiskey .
- Whiskey .
- This is a very interesting house you have , Herr Poelzig .
Has an atmosphere , kind of uh ...
- It is indeed hard to describe .
As hard to describe as life or ,
or death .
It may well be an atmosphere of death .
This place was built on the ruins
of that same Fort Marmaris that our unfortunate friend ,
the driver , described so vividly .
Herr Poelzig commanded Marmaris
during the last years of the war .
He 's perhaps sentimental about this spot .
And as for the house being interesting ,
architectural
it could not be otherwise .
Engineer Poelzig is one of Austria " s greatest architects .
- Dr. Werdegast is one of Hungary 's greatest psychiatrists .
- Allow me to introduce myself more fully .
I 'm Peter Alison , one of America 's greatest writers
of unimportant books .
- Oh , you 're an author , a novelist ?
What kind of things do you do ?
- Mysteries .
- To you , my friend .
To your charming wife .
And to love .
- You all right , Joan ?
Thought you were asleep .
- You are frightened , doctor ?
You are our host .
- At your service , madame .
You must be indulgent of Dr. Werdegast 's weakness .
He is the unfortunate victim
of one of the commoner phobias , but in an extreme form .
He has an intense and all-consuming horror of cats .
- Come darling , you must go back to bed .
You 're not strong enough .
- He is quite right .
You had a severe shock .
You must sleep .
- Goodnight , gentlemen .
Joan .
- I leave my presumption , but I must emphasize
the extreme importance of Mrs. Alison having complete quiet .
Sleep .
I gave her a very powerful narcotic
and I 'm sure it will be effective soon .
Her condition is not sufficiently serious
to be cause for alarm but , it is decidedly delicate .
Rest is the important thing .
- What curious changes it made in her ?
You must have noticed it .
- It is perhaps the narcotic .
Hyoscine affects certain people very oddly .
One cannot be sure .
Sometimes these cases take strange forms .
The victim becomes in a sense , mediumistic .
A vehicle for all the intangible forces
in operation around her .
- Sounds like a lot of supernatural baloney to me .
- Supernatural perhaps .
Baloney , perhaps not .
There are many things under the sun .
I shall show you your rooms .
- Strange about the cat .
Joan seemed so curiously affected when you killed it .
- That was coincidence , I think .
However , certain Asian books say
that the black cat is the living embodiment of evil .
And that 's that evil interest into
the nearest living thing .
It is ...
- The black cat does not die .
Those same books , if I 'm not mistaken ,
teach that the black cat is deathless .
Deathless is evil .
It is the origin of the common superstition ,
that the cat with nine lives .
You will sleep here , Vitus .
- Thank you .
- Night .
- Goodnight , gentlemen .
- Goodnight , Vitus .
Sleep well .
An extremely interesting and capable man .
- Yes .
- I hope you will be comfortable .
- Thank you .
- My room adjoins Mrs. Alison 's
if you would like to be near her .
Yes , thank you .
Do you mind if I keep this door open ?
- I 'd sleep in a cold sweat if you didn 't .
You know ,
this is a very tricky house .
Kinda place where I like to have company .
So , this guy , Poelzig 's a great architect ?
Yes , one of the greatest .
- Well , I suppose we 've got to have architects , too .
If I wanted to build a nice , cozy ,
unpretentious insane asylum , he 'd be the man for it .
You think Mrs. Alison will be well enough
to go on to Grumbach in the morning ?
I think so .
- That 'll be swell .
- Now , Vitus , we have something to settle , we two .
- You were seeking me , Hjalmar ?
- I beg your pardon .
Where is my wife ?
- Very well , Vitus .
I shall take you to her .
- Next time , I go to Niagara Falls .
- You will come alone , Vitus .
- Wait here .
And this was the entrance to the gun turrets .
Don 't you recognize it ?
I can still sense death in the air .
There is still death in the air .
It is just as much on the mind today as ever .
And this is the old chart room for the long range guns .
The guns are gone , but the charts are still here .
Now you see Vitus , I have cared for her tenderly and well .
You will find her almost as beautiful
as when you last saw her .
She died two years after the war .
How ?
- Of pneumonia .
She was never very strong , you know .
- And the child ?
Our daughter ?
Dead .
- And why is she ...
Why is she like this ?
- Is she not beautiful ?
I wanted to have her beauty always .
I loved her too , Vitus .
- Lies .
All lies , Hjalmar .
You killed her .
You killed her as I am about to kill you !
Ah !
- Come , Vitus .
Are we men or are we children ?
Of what use are all these melodramatic gestures ?
You say your soul was killed
and that you have been dead all these years .
And what of me ?
Did we not both die here in Marmaris 15 years ago ?
Are we any the less victims of the war
than those whose bodies were torn asunder ?
Are we not both the living dead
and now you come to me , playing at being an avenging angel ,
childishly thirsting for my blood .
We understand each other too well .
We know too much of life .
We shall play a little game , Vitus ,
a game of death , if you like ,
but under any circumstances , we shall have to wait
until these people are gone ,
until we are alone .
Until tomorrow .
What is it , Hjalmar ?
- Oh , it 's nothing .
Only an accident on the road below .
I want you to stay in this room all day tomorrow , Karen .
You are the very core and meaning of my life .
No one shall take you from me , not even Vitus .
Not even your father .
- Not yet , Domo .
Put that away .
We will bide our time .
Other lives are involved .
And this place is so undermined with dynamite
that the slightest mistake by one of us
would cause the destruction of all .
Until I tell you different , you are his servant , not mine .
- Peter ?
- Good morning .
Have you slept well ?
I must examine the dressing .
- Dressing ?
I don 't remember .
The bus .
We were in the bus and we fell ...
I don 't remember anything after that .
- You don 't ?
Where is Peter ?
Is he all right ?
- He is not in his room .
He is perhaps at breakfast .
Will you sit down ?
- What happened , Doctor ?
What is this place ?
- This is the home of my friend , Herr Poelzig .
- You will forgive this intrusion .
I came to inquire after the health of my charming guest .
- This is Engineer Poelzig , our host .
- Where is Peter , uh , Mr. Alison ?
- I think he is breakfasting .
I 'll send for him .
Are you worried , Vitus ?
- About myself , no .
- The girl ?
- Perhaps .
- Oh .
You 're interested .
- Maybe .
- I thought so .
Well , I 'm not .
Only spiritually .
Spiritually ?
- Tonight is the dark of the moon .
We shall gather and
you 'd better come , Vitus .
The ceremony will interest you .
- Don 't pretend , Hjalmar .
There was nothing spiritual in your eyes
when you looked at that girl .
You plan to keep her here .
- Perhaps .
I intend to let her go .
- Is that a challenge , Vitus ?
- Yes , if you dare to fight it out alone .
- Do you dare play chess with me for her ?
- Yes .
I will even play you chess for her ,
provided if I win , they are free to go .
- You won 't win , Vitus .
- Hurt ?
- Not a bit .
What happened last night ?
Did I do anything silly ?
- Silly ?
How could you do anything that wasn 't entirely lovely ?
Do you feel well enough to leave , darling ?
- I 'd feel well enough to leave
if I didn 't feel well enough to leave .
I don 't like this place .
- You don 't like it ?
You haven 't had breakfast yet .
- I don 't like Mr. Pigslow or whatever his name is .
- Poelzig .
Poelzig .
- Hurry up and get dressed , darling .
I 'll explain everything to Mr. Poelzig .
- All right .
- Come down when you 're ready .
- He wants to know our version of the accident .
- An American !
And will you tell me about the accident , please ?
- Well , Mrs. Alison , Dr. Werdegast and I
were on our way to Grumbach .
- Grumbach , it 's my home .
What a beautiful place .
What grandeur , what charm .
You have chosen very wisely , sir .
Grumbach is a pearl of the Carpathian Mountains ...
- I beg your pardon , sir .
Grumbach , it 's very nice in its way .
But it cannot compare with Pristion .
Pristion is my home .
There is a place .
Sport if you want sport .
Quiet if you want quiet .
Gaiety if you want the gaiety .
Pristion is God 's gift to young lover ...
- Pristion used to be all right .
10 , 15 years ago , but now ,
Grumbach is a place .
- Sir , you 're carrying it a little bit too far .
- How about the accident , Lieutenant .
I think it was due almost entirely to the rain .
Part of the road gave away ,
the bus tipped over and crashed , that 's all .
- Very well .
May I have your names ?
Werdegast , Dr. Vitus Werdegast .
Peter Alison .
- You gentlemen can be reached here ?
- Oh , you 've been very kind , Herr Poelzig ,
but Mrs. Alison and I must get back down to Visegrád .
You see , Mrs. Alison must communicate
with her parents in Vienna .
May we ride back with you to Visegrád ?
- I should be very happy to accommodate you ,
unfortunately , we of the gendarmerie
go about on bicycles .
It would be very inconvenient for madame .
- I 'm afraid it is impossible to get a train
out of Visegrád until the express goes through
at 11 o 'clock tonight .
I shall be most happy to send you down then .
- Thank you , gentlemen .
I should be very sorry if I 've inconvenienced you ,
and I shall be very sorry too ,
if you do not decide to go on to Grumbach .
- Pristion .
- Dr. Werdegast , I feel sure that Mrs. Alison
is well enough to go on ...
- I beg your pardon , but do you play chess ?
- No .
I used to play a very good hand of poker .
- Well , if you don 't mind , I think
we 'll go on with our game .
- Please don 't think we don 't appreciate
your hospitality , Herr Poelzig .
Mrs. Alison is still quite shaken up
from the accident , you know
and feels she wants to get back to Vienna .
Now , if you could send us down to Visegrád ,
I 'm sure we can hire a car there
that will take us on to Budapest ,
or at least far enough to get a decent train .
- But of course .
I shall be very sorry to see you go ,
but if you and Mrs. Alison think best , why ...
I want you to take Mr. and Mrs. Alison down to Visegrád .
Now , you realize of course , that this is against
the advice of Dr. Werdegast
and you will have to assume the full responsibility .
- Oh , but I 'm quite sure she 'll be all right .
- Then we will go on with our game .
- I 'm sorry sir , the car is out of commission .
It will take some time to repair it .
- Oh , Mr. Alison .
You see , I use the car so seldom myself ,
I 'm afraid you 'll just have to be patient .
- Then may I use your telephone ?
I 'll telephone the hotel in Visegrád
and ask them to send a car .
- Of course , of course .
Take the gentleman to the telephone .
Did you get the hotel ?
- No .
The phone 's dead .
- You hear that , Vitus ?
The phone is dead .
Even the phone is dead .
- Come along , Joan .
We 're getting outta here , fast .
What happened ?
- Never mind , darling .
Just stay close to me and don 't say anything .
We 're leaving if we have to walk to Visegrád .
Oh , never mind about the baggage .
We 'll send for that later .
The main thing is to go and go quickly .
Someone 's taken my automatic .
- Check mate .
You lose , Vitus .
We 're leaving .
Open the door .
- I hope you won 't carry this too far , Hjalmar .
Child , I hope you 're not afraid of me .
- Where 's Peter ?
What have you done with him ?
- I ?
Surely you don 't think I ...
- It was your servant who struck him down .
Where is he , where is he ?
- Shhh .
Please , child , listen to me .
We 're all in danger .
Poelzig is a mad beast , I know .
I know , I 've seen the proof .
He took Karen , my wife .
Murdered her , and murdered my child .
- And you let him live ?
- I wait my time .
It shall be soon , very soon .
Until then , I must do his bidding .
That is why my servant obeys him .
Did you ever hear of Satanism ,
the worship of the devil , of evil ?
Herr Poelzig is a great modern priest of that ancient cult
and tonight , dark of the moon ,
the rites of Lucifer are celebrated .
And if I 'm not mistaken , he intends you
to play a part of that ritual ,
a very important part .
- Oh !
- Shh .
There , child .
Be brave ,
no matter how hopeless it all seems .
Be brave , it is your only chance .
- Who are you ?
I 've never seen you before , have I ?
- No , I don 't think you have .
- I 'm Karen , Madame Poelzig .
Karen ?
Not Karen Werdegast ?
- Yes .
Yes , how did you know my name ?
- Well , I ,
I know your father .
- Oh no , you are mistaken .
My father died in prison .
Herr Poelzig married my mother .
She died when I was very young .
And he married you ?
You 're his wife ?
- Yes .
- Karen , listen to me .
Your father is not dead .
I know , I know .
He 's here in this very house .
He 's come for you .
Karen , do you understand me ?
Your father has come for you .
No , Hjalmar !
Please !
- Dark of the moon is tonight .
- We better hurry .
Guests will soon be here for the ceremony .
Peter !
Please let me go !
Please !
Don 't , no , please , don 't !
- Stop struggling , little fool .
There 's the way out .
Come .
This way .
- Peter , where is he ?
- Never mind him .
But you will be dead soon if you don 't come with me quickly .
- And Karen .
Karen is dead .
- No , I mean Karen , your daughter .
Madame Poelzig .
- What do you mean ?
- She 's alive .
Here in this house .
She 's Poelzig 's wife .
- Where is she ?
Where is Karen , my daughter ?
- Joan .
Joan .
- Do you know what I 'm going to do to you now ?
No ?
Did you ever see an animal skinned Hjalmar ?
That 's what I 'm going to do to you now .
Tear the skin from your body ...
slowly .
Bit by bit .
How does it feel to hang
on your own embalming rack , Hjalmar ?
- Joan , the key !
The key !
Let me help you .
- Stand back , Werdegast !
Get away , Werdegast .
He wanted to help us .
- You poor fool .
I only tried to help .
Now go , please , go .
It 's the red switch , isn 't it , Hjalmar ?
The red switch ignites the dynamite .
Five minutes .
You and I and your rotten color
will be no more .
It has been a good game .
Please , stop !
- Visegrád , Budapest .
- Darling , here 's a review of Triple Murder .
In Triple Murder , Mr. Alison 's latest mystery thriller ,
he fulfills the promise shown by the 69th
prime in the purple spot .
We feel however , that Mr. Alison has , in a sense ,
overstepped the bounds in the matter of credibility .
These things could never , by the furthest stretch
of the imagination actually happen .
We could wish that Mr. Alison would confine himself
to the possible instead of letting
his melodramatic imagination run away with him .